basic
stuff that we always forget. I'm sure
you won't turn on the green button when
you want to speak.
All right. Okay. So, let's call this
meeting of the uh China Historic
Preservation Board uh to order here a
little after 6 on the 13th of January.
And let's start with our roll call.
And let's go with uh Amber
>> here.
>> Okay. And David
>> Thank you. And Gary
>> here.
Okay, very good. And uh Don,
I didn't hear from Don. I don't know if
anybody did. Okay. Uh Josh
>> here.
>> Elizabeth
>> Patrick
>> Patrick B here.
>> B. Sorry. Yes.
Okay. Kelly
>> here.
Patrick Van
is absent and uh John
>> here.
>> Fantastic.
All right. Very good. Let's go ahead and
go to our agenda
and um between Did you say Charles
between two and three? One and two.
Okay. Well, let's go ahead and go with
some uh introductions.
Why don't we uh just have every member
of the board introduce themselves? maybe
if you have an officer position on the
board, if you can remember how long
you've been serving and uh then John,
we'll look forward to hearing a little
bit about you. Let's start over here
with Patrick.
>> Uh Patrick, uh this is the beginning of
my fourth year on the board.
>> Amber Conwell, vice chair. Um I think
this is my fifth year or sixth year.
Josh,
>> do we Okay, [laughter]
starting six.
Uh I'm Josh Chrysler. I we started at
the same time. So like uh we're just
starting the sixth year. Um and I am
currently the secretary.
>> And we're going to pass over you for
now, John, so you can be last. Milward
Simpson, six years.
>> Uh David Benner, uh I'm starting my
ninth year.
>> Gary Sims, 12 years.
And I'm Kelly Sevir and I'm a new member
to the board as well. Started I think in
July of last year. Um but this is the
beginning of my first official term I
believe.
>> And John, we have two other members. Don
Herald who's a longtime member, does a
lot of our marketing and he's had a
difficult time attending recently for
some life circumstances, but he's still
on the board. And uh Patrick Van sent me
an email last month said that he was
reappointed to the board. He's pleased
about that. We may not see uh much of
him uh for a while in person anyway
because of the issues, health issues
he's dealing with right now. So uh
welcome John. Tell us I'm sorry.
>> Oh yeah, Elizabeth. Sorry.
>> That's okay.
Um Elizabeth Gier, sorry I couldn't make
it. I have a cold today. Um, but I have
been on the board for just over I think
a year and a half now.
>> Fantastic. Hope you hope you feel
better.
>> And [snorts] how about our staff? You
would you may or may not have met our
our staff who's present and our city
council representative.
>> Oh, yep. I'm city councilman Ken Escoel.
W three
>> and a liaison from the council to the
board. Charles
>> Charles Bloom, planning and development
director. I've been here since 2018.
>> Aaron,
>> uh Aaron Fagen. I'm one of the planners
in the office and I've been working with
the board I think maybe a year, maybe a
little under a year, but I've been with
the planning office for five years.
>> Yeah. Please, please come around the
corner.
Hi, Morgan. Hi, Morgan Dennis. Planner
one with planning and development.
>> How long have you been in the with
planning Morgan?
>> Uh, four months.
>> She looks at her watch. [laughter]
>> I think like four months. Yeah.
>> Okay. Great.
All right. So, uh, John, tell us a
little bit about yourself.
Good evening. Name's John Berdick. This
is my very first meeting. Great to be
here and very nice to meet everyone in
the room. It's a pleasure. Um I'm a
recent uh transplant to city of
Cheyenne. I've just been here five
months, but I hopped right on it and
applied for this position. Um I am a
retired history teacher and school
administrator. Uh 30 years with my
school district teaching US and world
history. I've also worked as a history
consultant for my school district. Uh
originally from San Diego, but have
lived in places like Michigan and Summit
County, Colorado,
which is by uh Silverthorn and uh
Breenidge.
Uh love living in Cheyenne. Many people
ask me, "What brought you out here?" And
then I I ask them right back, "Well,
what brought you out here?"
wide open spaces, clean air, friendly
people, plenty of fun things to do. Uh,
today I was on a epic road trip, drove
to Fort Laramie, toured that whole
property, took some great pictures, and
then came back to be on time for this
meeting. So, it's great to meet
everybody. I should clarify, it's John
Charles,
but please call me Chuck.
I so I go by Chuck with because my
middle name is Charles but John is the
legal name which I put on my
application. So great to be here. Thank
you all.
Welcome Chuck. We're very very glad to
have you.
All right. So this is kind of a time of
uh transitions every year and the second
item on the agenda is election of
officers and uh colleagues I'm going to
announce a personal transition of mine.
Uh I'm going to be stepping off this
board um as of the end of the next
month's meeting in February. Um life
circumstances as a full-time caregiver
and shifting priorities have made this
something I need to do now and uh was
probably only going to serve till the
end of this year anyway, but uh I need
to do so now. And I think the timing is
good with the transition of officers and
uh going into a fresh strategic plan
with kind of a a new profile on the
board. So, um I'll have a chance to kind
of say goodbye to you all next month,
but I've really really enjoyed serving
with all of you. I'm proud of what we've
accomplished. I really have enjoyed
every minute of my six years on this
board and the things we've been able to
do together. Um do have a couple of
regrets. just we just didn't quite get
that uh that uh demolition by neglect
ordinance over the finish line as close
as we got. Maybe you'll all try that
again sometime, but I think it was worth
uh worth every bit of the effort that we
put in. So, um it's been a real real
pleasure serving with you and I'm not
going anywhere. I'm going to stay
supportive as much as I can of all
things historic preservation and uh be
involved in my capacity as a citizen to
the greatest extent I can. So, thank you
all for your continuing service. It's
been a pleasure. With that, um it's time
to elect new officers.
And um I think what we've kind of been
in the habit of doing uh is kind of a
nomination of a slate or I think that's
one of the viable ways we can do this.
Um and I guess I would ask if there is
uh anybody who would like to express
their interest in serving in in any of
these positions particularly
um including the uh chair, vice chair
and secretary. Is there anyone who's
interested in in being considered to be
elected you know to an officer position
>> hold that high Amber
chair and if I may note right now in
historically in the past the secretary
had taken minutes but we have been doing
the minutes for the secretary so just in
case anyone's scared of being the
secretary we still are completing the
minutes,
>> but the city has rendered that a much uh
less burdensome role, which we're all
have been very grateful for. Um, is
there anyone who is interested in
serving as vice chair who is currently
not in an officer position or secretary?
I could do secretary.
>> Okay, David.
Um, Elizabeth
I feel like uh I should wait till after
these contracts are completed before
stepping up in a larger role.
>> Okay, that that makes sense to me as
well. Um okay. Uh is there anyone who
Let's let me put it this way. Is there
anyone who absolutely is not or would
not be willing to serve in an officer
position if you were nominated?
Okay, very good.
Well then, um given my situation, I'm
I'd like to go ahead and be the person
to um uh make a motion for a slate and
we can have a discussion. I would move
chair for uh Amber Conwell.
I would move vice chair for Josh
Chrysler.
And I would move David Benner for
secretary.
And then I'll call for a second. Second.
>> Okay. Any uh any discussion.
All right. Hearing none. We have a
motion and a second on the floor. Um
I'll ask for a a voice vote. All those
in favor, please say I.
>> I.
Congratulations. I bake. Get to work
now. Yay.
Um, thank you Amber, Josh, and David. I
couldn't be more happy leaving the board
feeling that this uh leadership is in
great hands. So, really appreciate your
willingness to step up and serve in an
additional capacity on this board. Um,
and these uh could you remind me,
Charles or Erin, what is the term of
these? Do we elect these folks every
year or do they serve longer than that?
>> It's every year.
>> Every year. Okay. So you'd stand and
then there is a term limit though for
officers I think. Isn't it two two terms
>> for officers?
>> Well, it's three years for
term members for to be on the board.
It's a three-year term. But
for the um
chair and vice chair secretary, those
are one-year terms. then you elect every
January for a new slate of officers, but
I don't know if there's a limit. He's
looking it up real quick to see if
>> Yeah. Yeah. I thought it was he could be
elect reelected one time, but uh
>> yeah, I think that but Charles Charles
will confirm once he's found it. Okay,
great. Um let's u and thank you again.
Let's move on to approval of minutes for
the December 9 meeting. Hopefully
everybody had a chance to take a look at
those. Is there a motion?
>> I had uh one comment.
>> Corrections. Okay.
>> Yeah. Um under the pump house update
section, there was something that
mentioned Patrick Van had made an
amendment to the resolution regarding
demo of the building, but Patrick was
absent last meeting, I believe. So, I'm
not sure what who
that was supposed to be. Remember when
we were having a a long deliberation
about what we wanted to see in a
proposed substitute resolution? Was that
maybe an amendment that you proposed,
Patrick?
>> Seconded it
>> or seconded or something
>> to get a quote for what the demolition
would cost of the pump house, I believe,
is what it was referring to.
If I remember the the conversation
correctly,
what I was referring to was that we as a
board had made a a previous commitment
of 2.5 at the November meeting. At the
December meeting, that was increased to
to to 4 million because
>> I remember your you had questions about
that.
>> Yeah, I had questions about that because
that's what Charles was recommending to
the to the council in terms of the
dollar amount. So that's what I recall.
>> Do the minutes reflect that Patrick Van
was present?
>> They reflect that he is absent.
>> Okay.
>> All right. Does anybody recall having
asked that uh that provision in the
substitute proposed language be
included?
>> If I and I if I recall correctly, we did
not make a a motion. We just basically
went with a recommendation that the 4
million be the the board's position.
>> Okay. Well, maybe a way to fix that
would be Let me find it here.
House.
>> Yeah. Kelly, what which of the bullets
is that
in the minutes?
>> It's the very first bullet point on page
three where it starts background was
given on the pump house. added amount of
the revenue to calculate the cost of
demolition.
Why why
don't we just strike that sentence? Does
that make sense? Or should we consult
with the recording of the meeting? Maybe
whatever the the recording says, we can
amend the minutes that way and go with
that.
>> Chair, yeah, we can go back and look at
listen to the minutes and correct it.
>> How about that, colleagues? We just say
now that we'll approve uh the minutes um
pending an amendment based on the
recording
for the uh demolition
portion.
It's a complicated motion to approve the
minutes. Does anybody want to make it?
>> I so move.
>> Okay. Is there a second?
>> I'll second.
>> Okay. Is there discussion? Everybody
understand what we're voting on? You're
just going to go Eron's going to go back
listen to it and correct it as as the
recording indicates.
All right. Very good. All those in
favor, please say I.
>> I.
>> All right. Any oppose?
>> Okay. Um, any conflicts of interest to
or exparte communications to disclose
between the last meeting and this one?
Okay. I don't see any audience members
here. Is there anybody online
other than Elizabeth? Okay.
All right. Let's go to a report from our
fearless city council representative,
Councilman Escoel. Thanks for being here
as usual.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chair. Um,
last night at our city council meeting,
we did the same thing that you just did.
we nominated in the approved the
officers for 2026.
So, Councilman Tom Crave will be the new
council president. Uh Pete Labor will be
our vice president.
Uh Dr. Kathy Edmonds will be chair of
public service and I will be chair of
finance.
Um
probably the
the biggest issue we dealt with last
night was administrative warrants.
Uh there's been
uh four or five instanc instances across
the city uh with uh safety violations
and our building inspectors have not
been able to get in touch with the
owners. uh the administrative warrant
would need to go to a judge under
probable cause for that safety violation
under affidavit
um for us to further inspect those
dangerous situations.
Um, for example, we we did have one in
uh our neighborhood and had it not been
for uh the gentleman that owned this
property's dog getting out and biting
the neighbor
lady in our compliance showing up. Uh
upon um
visiting with the owner, they noticed
that he had put a wood burning stove
that was vented through the hole in the
side of his garage.
It was in between his and the neighbor's
house. So whenever he was
lighting fires in his garage, the
cinders were falling upon the neighbor's
roof. That that's that's something that
we take seriously, especially with uh
things that we've seen across the
country with fires spreading in
neighborhoods. Uh we've had two close
calls with grass fires, one out north
and one out uh just in the past year and
the dry conditions will continue to
exasperate that possibility. So anyways,
um we're looking to do some amendments
on it. Uh there were three no votes. Uh
we we'll see what the committee and the
sponsors do going forward. Uh we had two
public hearings on transfers of liquor
licenses. One was from the the green
door and scooters to
establishments that closed down over
here on Lincolnway and those went to
AC's range which is the golf simulator
uh racetrack simulators. Uh you can
shoot guns and rifle simulators over
here off uh 15th Street and then the
other one to Westby Edge just down the
block. Um
we also are moving forward with our
resolutions on approving our budgets. Um
those will both be coming to my finance
committee
and
I have this one cir circled.
Um, the other committee I I serve on
board is the community development block
grant advisory council and we work with
those HUD funds to fund a lot of
lowincome
projects around town.
uh
Habitat for Humanity, for example, My
Front Door Needs, Kamia Shelter. Uh we
have about half a dozen of those
nonprofits that we'll be reviewing here
in the coming weeks uh to fund with the
money that we do get. Uh also, they use
some reallocations of funds. I think I
talked about this before, but we did uh
approve the annexation of the land that
is north of Walmart, Sam's Club out
there between there and Story Boulevard
or the affordable housing
uh units that are going to be going in
there about 180 uh units. And that
that's uh a multifaceted financing
program that we're doing with the city
with uh some funds that were donated to
the city uh by one of the
uh um
new companies that came into town, the
related digital uh one of the
um
new companies that has a data center out
south of town. uh that was a $3.5
million donation to the city to put in
that help us afford this pro project. So
that along with the CBDG funds and the
Wasatch group that's coming in to help
us with that. Uh it's something that
ever since I've been on city council
we've been trying to do is address this
affordable housing issue. Uh the reason
I mentioned that too because a lot of
people get
uh low-income housing and affordable
housing mixed up. Well, the advisory
council with community development block
grant money, that's more your lowincome
housing, whereas this other project is
the affordable housing.
Uh
what else do I have here?
Uh tomorrow night we start committee of
the whole
on our six penny projects.
Um
the mayor sent us a letter of his
recommendations.
Uh and mostly these are
um public safety projects that have to
do with our fire department, police
department. There is some greenway uh
money that we're going to be talking
about. Also, the remodeling of this
building.
Uh
>> that's about a $22 million ask. Uh as
many of you know, we've had to shut this
building down uh three or four times
over the past few years. Uh and then
also this week we have what we do at the
beginning of the year after we elect our
officers is have a goal setting session
that'll be Thursday night and all the
members of the council submitted
what their ideas are for our goals going
forward. Um I have that list here in
each councilman's recommendations if you
want to hear that. Is this something you
might be interested in? Because there
are some
>> historic preservation related.
>> Yeah.
>> Great. Let's hear those first.
>> Um Okay.
Um well, Dr. Aldridge put in to finalize
six ballot and plan to educate the
public about that. And and of course,
we've always talked about the pump
house. uh that one um
but members of the council have
expressed interest in trying to fund
that with other funds. Um, also a m
multifaceted funding through
uh historic Cheyenne through the
cultural trust fund grants and uh
through some of our general fund reserve
money and using the pump house for some
of our own
u
programs and and departments of
using that building. Um, part of the
other part of it I can't talk about yet.
Um,
let's see. Um, Dr. Kathy Edmonds wants
to implement a project management
process system that can be easily
accessed. We're we're going more with
open gov and online.
Um
I down to finish the goals that we
haven't funded in the past and uh looked
at u running a pilot project or
demonstration project in what we call
the me lumber triangle on the north end
of Reed Avenue corridor. We have almost
$2 million left. Um, we're trying to
leverage that money with the Wami
Business Council so we can start that
project before
the six penny ballot that that's an
ambitious schedule because that's only
eight months. But I think we need to
show the public that this is a project
that we're dedicated to finishing. And a
couple of the other members also
mentioned that on here. Uh, Councilman
Moody wants to improve crosswalk safety
and evaluate the reports that we're
getting on improvements with our fleet
management. Uh, their building there is
just too small for a lot of our larger
vehicles that now have to go in there.
So, for example, our new ladder trucks
when when they have to go in
um just for a tire rotation,
they have to move back and forth to get
to the lift
like six times in order order to move
maneuver it in to where it needs to be.
Um
Dr.
he wants to keep on top of the projects
that I mentioned moving forward and he
mentions the 15th Street
uh project.
Um he wants to discuss implementing the
public information strategy so
you uh our residents know what we're
doing and why we're doing it and and
they get the proper information. They're
not getting it from the internet or
groups that are making stuff up.
Um, Councilman Seagrave wants to ident
identify funding streams to support the
use of revenue bonds for completion of
the listed community recreation events
projects.
and he wants to do all the projects that
they have in their pipeline over the
next three years, which is another
ambitious project program because part
of that one includes
um an indoor turf facility that a lot of
us really wanted have for the kids here
so they could uh practice all the
outdoor sports that in the winter that
they they participate in the spring and
summer. [snorts] Um, Councilman White,
he also uh talked about both the 15th
Street project and Reed Avenue corridor
projects. And Councilman Wolf wants to
develop a city-wide strategic plan to
identify who will be responsible for
overseeing this effort and uh wants to
include consideration of moving to
another form of government such as
having a city manager which we discussed
about five or six years ago. Right.
Um, I guess moving to the end of our
agenda.
That was about it. We
Yeah, that was because I talked about
those two other things earlier.
know if you have any questions about six
penny goal setting uh any of the other
items on the agenda annexations.
>> Anybody have any questions for
our council?
>> I just I just had one out of just kind
of personal interest on administrative
warrants.
>> Um is it just solely just on safety
issues or is there going to be like an
any discussion about health concerns? Uh
I
>> it's public safety
>> like it's just safety.
>> Okay.
>> I think one of the things that when
you've talked about demolition blind by
neglect
um no Charles I think that's something
that probably
uh could be used in a severe situation.
He's not in his head. Yes.
All right. Thanks. Other questions.
>> Well, I would say uh congratulations and
uh the progress on the affordable
housing. I've been following that too
and um sounds like there's some good
things coming and maybe some hopeful
things on the the solution to funding
the pump house uh restoration at least
to some degree. So, that's exciting and
promising too. And um I just got a
message from the governor here says your
resignation is not accepted.
>> The governor [laughter]
>> bad chance. Okay.
>> Unless you're running for his position.
[laughter]
>> Well, thanks and um um thanks for taking
on the the finance committee leadership
position. I imagine your um time in the
appropriations committee is going to
serve you well.
>> All right. Excellent. Let's move to uh
report from planning and development
department.
>> Charles, chair, members of the board. Um
really we don't have too much going on
other than the day the day-to-day
activities. Um we still have a lot of
different developments that are
proposed. Um recently we've seen a lot
of new interest in apartment complexes.
We have the one still going in downtown
which is actually taking a lot of shape.
So that is 101 units that's located
right up here on 19th in O'Neal that was
created with tax increment financing. Um
tax increment financing is a new tool
that we really started to roll out in
2020 here in Cheyenne. It had been used
in the past a long time ago and it had
been sort of swept under the rug and
hadn't been used in a long time. So we
dusted it off and started to use it
again. Um, for the first time, we're
actually seeing an increment that is
being generated from one of our tax
increment financing projects. This is
basically taxes that were they were
frozen at one point in time. This is the
hitching post when the property was
essentially worth nothing.
um that tax distribution that went to
all the different tax agencies like
schools, city, county, uh mosquito
control districts, you know, any special
district uh that got money, that
dispersement was frozen for a period of
time. So what the goal is is when a new
development takes shape, it is assessed,
pay taxes, but they're now paying a new
level of taxes and that additional tax
increment
um that is used to pay off the public
investment that they made. It reimburses
them for that public investment. So,
we're finally seeing some return on the
hitching post. Although it's not uh
it's not in accordance with the timeline
they initially proposed because they got
a little bit of a late start there, it
is occurring and it will very much very
likely catch up and make the lender
whole again. So, that was the the first
uh success in our tax increment
financing. The Stencil project, which is
the multif family right here, um that is
continuing to move forward. um that is
is following their timeline. We're
expecting to see revenue from that in
the near future. Um the urban renewal uh
authority has directed staff to explore
uh opening up the toolbox for urban
renewal to the entire community. Um so
in February they intend to uh pass
forward a citywide blight designation
which is the first step to open the
toolbox. um that blight designation will
be acted upon by them and then referred
to the governing body for discussion
ultimate adoption. Uh declaring parts of
the community blight doesn't
automatically open the door for every
project to use urban renewal uh dollars
or tax increment financing. What it does
is it says you are able to explore that
and if your development truly needs that
to stand up to close a financial gap
then you can utilize that. So we're
continuing to evaluate how that will
look in the community uh to see uh where
we can utilize that tool in the
community. Um it is a new year fiscal
year 26. Um we are presently uh working
on uh continuing to streamline our
processes to make sure that we are
providing timely reviews of different
projects. We are seeing a lot of
pressure with large data center
developments that seem to have sparked a
lot of interest in the community. Um so
it seems like every day we are looking
another direction and another one wants
to to pop into town. So there'll be a
lot of discussion that will be uh coming
up on that
>> and nuclear power. Did we read about
that?
>> Yes, there was a a discussion uh well
there was an article that was released
late last week regarding a partnership
with Meta Group and Terra Energy I
believe um to provide uh funding. META
would provide funding for up to eight
nuclear Natrium Natrium nuclear reactors
and that would be located in conjunction
with some of their sites in the in the
United States. So we haven't heard from
them exactly as to what their plans are
here, but we would not doubt that they
would um be interested in this location.
Uh something we continue to work to move
forward on is our comprehensive plan
update which will have a historic
preservation element as well. It'll help
set some of the policies and the goals
for historic preservation in the city.
Again, we'll be keeping the the board
involved. One of the other items that we
will be working on in that um plan
update will be data center development
standards um evaluating best practices
and see where we need to go. One of the
big things with data centers right now
is we do see a lot of uh property tax
revenue when they are located because
you're we are collecting property tax on
the land value plus the structure value
and the fixtures that are within that.
So if you have a building that's the
same size as a Walmart store, you're
looking at about three to four times
that valuation because of the equipment
that's in there. The other item that we
collect uh tax dollars on if they are in
the city is the electricity sales tax.
We have a special agreement with
franchise tax where we get approximately
it's about 11% of their power bill comes
into the city. We're seeing a shift in
the data centers where a lot of them are
starting to bring their own power which
means they're behind the meter which
means we won't be seeing that revenue.
So, we need to evaluate what our best
practices are for for these data centers
as they come in because we want to make
sure they still are a community benefit.
So, lots of different uh elements we're
looking at here in the community. Uh
lots of uh changes we're continuing to
try to move forward with making sure
that we are um trying to keep the
processes easier and more simple because
we want to be able to adopt or adapt and
uh shift gears quickly. One thing that
is truly uh unique that is actually was
just introduced to the council last week
and will be going to committee um next
Monday is we've changed we propose to
change our accessory dwelling unit
regulations. What is an accessory
dwelling unit? It basically is when you
have a second dwelling unit on your
property. Right now, if you are in any
zone district where you have a home, you
are able to have one accessory dwelling
unit, whether it be a second building on
your property, a basement, apartment, um
provided you live in that structure.
It's one of those is owner occupied.
There's a proposal to remove the owner
occupied requirement. So, it would just
allow for any single family home to have
a second unit on that lot, whether it be
a basement apartment or be a standalone
um apartment that would be in the back.
These would not have to be owner
occupied. These would just be the
building for two units. The one caveat
is that if you do take advantage of
that, you will have to make sure that
your building is built to building
codes, which means you have to have um
adequate egress like egress windows, a
separate entrance. Um you also have to
ensure that um you have that adequate
separation between the two units. So
that is uh moving forward to the council
right now. Um, in our eyes, it will give
us the ability to help aid those
property owners who may have bought a
somewhat historic home or just a
historic by time period home where they
may have had a basement apartment that
just happened to show up um, and it
might not meet the lot sizes or the lot
width requirements to allow for that
second unit. So, this gives them an
avenue to at least upgrade that home,
bring it up to a better life um safety
standard so they can continue to use
that as a two unit. So, we'll see where
that goes. Um that will be at public
services following the discussion on
warrants next week.
>> David,
>> yes.
I noticed there's little red and white
signs on the coal property south of
story in between powder house and
college or or uh Converse, excuse me.
Chair three to board member Benner.
That's a great observation. Uh right now
we are completing our last two county
pocket annexation initiatives. This was
a 2022 council goal. Uh the one up north
encompasses the Cole property which is
the area bounded by Powderhouse Story,
Converse, Walmart, Kohl's, all of that.
So that area is included in the
annexation. The Cole family is
supportive of the annexation. Also in
that big rectangular area, there is a
piece of land owned by the school
district and by the city. They have not
expressed opposition to that. In fact,
I'm pretty sure the city is in support
of it. Um there is another area of land
that's also included in the annexation
which is owned by the Edwards family
which is on the west or the east side of
Converse near Anderson Elementary
School. Um and that is included in that
county pocket annexation. So that whole
north area, it kind of leapfrogged and
jumped ahead of the others because of
other development actions going on um
and the confusion between multiple
jurisdictions. Um but annexing it brings
it in one jurisdiction which is
beneficial for drainage grading um and
also um subdividing the land. The final
county pocket annexation map um and
process has been initiated. Earlier this
week, Connor White, a planner two in our
department, he mailed out the final sets
of notice to a handful of properties.
That's about 10 to 12 properties located
um in South Cheyenne, like off of
Allison and Waltershide. a couple of
areas over off of um
um
Westland Road in that area and another
large uh piece of land um located on
Waltershide near Fox Farm. It's the
agricultural use. There's a a little
urban farm at that location that will
represent the last county pocket
annexation. So we will have one
uninterrupted area of city limits making
emergency response a lot uh more
predictable.
>> Question Gary,
>> can you update us on the house on 20th
Street? You brought it up last month,
the one across the street from the
governor's mansion.
>> Members of the board, I don't have any
updates on that. I apologize. I need to
get updates on it.
Um, chair through the only thing I have
is that he did recently submit a
building permit to finish out um the
interior and some of the exterior of the
building
and but it he
said that it is in accordance with what
you guys approved previously.
But we'll be watching.
>> Any other questions, Patrick? And then
Josh.
>> Um Charles, just a real quick I think
more of a comment than a question. Um if
I remember correctly, um
the uh use of urban renewal has been
really kind of challenging sometimes.
And I've seen some wonderful cultural
resources lost and some ugly, darn ugly
urban renewal projects. And I don't know
if there's a role for the preservation
of, you know, structures or cultural
resources, any of that issue. Um, it it
it scares me sometimes when I hear of
urban renewal and it it urban renewal in
my uh experience has been, you know,
demolish and put ugly stuff up and my
interpretation of ugly. Um, something
that's not compatible, something that's,
you know, probably not very uh, you
know, welldesigned and well constructed
and and that that scares me a little
bit, Charles. And it it's just a kind of
a a a concern that I that that I have in
my experience with not all but some
urban renewal projects
>> and related
>> and then yeah just added on to that did
did I understand correctly that the
urban renewal authority is preparing to
declare the entire city blighted is that
what you said
and and that's seems like an S surely
there are like
guidelines they have to follow to I'm
just very curious about that and what
the response to that is going to be
>> chair through you to the board members
making comments two things I'll address
board member's concern first um urban
renewal has given itself a terrible
terrible uh reputation over the years um
it really started back in I think it was
late 1940 40s it was the housing
enabling act is what started urban
renewal and then there's some
significant changes that were made I
believe in the '60s which opened up for
um more of what you call slum clearance
and that's where it got a huge bad name
where you see communities like Denver
where large blocks historic buildings
were torn down and demolished. Um
nowadays urban renewal really has
shifted into a tool to help remove the
gap um for developments. Um all of our
plans that we have put together they
will say what the purpose is for and the
purpose is usually for public facing
benefit um or public infrastructure. So
that means facade a remediation of
contamination. Uh that means
installation of water lines, sewer
lines, curb better sidewalk, street
furnishing, street trees, stuff like
that. Only once have we proposed
property acquisition. Um and then that
was stripped out by the
urban recommended for removal by the
urban renewal authority and then also
recommended for removal by the governing
body and that was for the hinds and the
whole and that was simply for
acquisition and control of the property.
Um and that doesn't mean that a city
would just take that property. they
would have to go through a condemnation
proceeding and then pay an appraisal
rate market value for that land. Um the
appetite for condemnation and slum
clearance it is not here right now. I
can comfortably say that even at the
last legislative session, there were
some proposed changes to urban renewal
and Representative Charles Scott out of
Nrona County, [clears throat] he had
proposed an amendment to ensure that
urban renewal
would not be allowed to be used to
acquire any property that had had a
residential occupant. So there there is
a statewide temperature on urban renewal
and property rights that the government
cannot take it take or acquire property.
I think this is very evident with the
warrant discussion we've recently had
that it would be 10fold.
Um regarding
the declaration of blight it really is a
technicality. Um the first step in urban
renewal is you need to declare an area
blight. There are nine criteria and a
catch-all criteria that range from
everything from poor platting, bad
connectivity, deteriorating curb,
gutter, sidewalk and street, flood
plane, risk of fire, risk of other
hazards. Um
there's also ones such as uh financial
issues where you know houses you know
could be underwater struct buildings
could be underwater financially a whole
variety of items to declare an area
blight. You only need to identify one of
those findings under state statute. That
could be as simple as looking around for
the first broken curb and gutter you see
in the community. It's everywhere. First
pothole. I challenge you to find the
first one that's close. Um, what the
light study does is it would identify
about five to six areas of the community
where there's some conditions that
exist. And the ultimate goal of a
renewal is once that first step is done,
it then opens a toolbox for one to apply
for a plan and project where they can
say, I want to take this piece of
property, whether it's vacant, whether
it's underutilized, and they want to
develop it. And just that new investment
in the community that is going to help
eliminate
uh the blight that is in an area nearby.
So every plan and project that is done
is a increase in investment in the
community which is in theory supposed to
help mitigate blight that surrounds it.
So your plan and project like the
stencil development um that one did
demonstrate blight on the actual project
site itself um but it didn't need to
because just that investment helps
trigger reinvestment in the area
surrounding surrounding it which has a
domino effect in eliminating those
conditions of blight. So essentially the
blight study sounds terrible. It sounds
like a bad idea to declare blight. it
just is opening up the toolbox and gives
a someone permission to try to do an
urban renewal project um where they
still have to go through a whole another
routine um to provide a plan for what
they want to do and then they have to go
through another exercise which is to
demonstrate after they put all their
numbers on the table their proforma all
their numbers and they have to identify
that this project wouldn't happen
unless you know the urban renewal uh tax
increment financing contribution was
made.
I'll get you the we'll get you the links
to it as it moves forward. Um but it's
not pointing out Josh's house or uh
Patrick's house or any or my house and
saying that's a that's blight.
>> I can see Josh Josh's wheels turning
trying to process all of this.
>> It's a lot. It is a lot. If there if
there are I guess some resources you can
point us to um that would be great just
to learn more about it. I can tell you
that um from my experience
tax increment financing could be a
really powerful thing um for cultural
improvements. There are some communities
around the country that for instance
have used the tiff mechanism um to
create arts districts or um turns turn
uh buildings into live work spaces for
artists and things like that. So it can
be a really kind of contemporary way to
accomplish cultural goals. I'm really
pleased that um we have one that we've
tried in the city that that sounds like
it's going to be proving itself out. And
I think if it proves that, you know, it
can um generate the revenue to reimburse
for the upfront expense, then it proves
that it works and then maybe the the
city would be wanting to do more and
more of it. So, I I think that's a
really potentially positive development
for the city.
Um, any other questions or comments on
anything
for Charles or the staff?
Okay, let me get back to the agenda
and we are on our normal process here,
the strategic goals report. Um, since we
uh have Elizabeth with us, Elizabeth, do
you want to I know we saw here late in
the day um a couple of uh PDF document
updates, but you want to go ahead and
verbally kind of tell us what's going on
with your two projects?
>> Yeah, so I can give um a quick overview
of what I've included on there. So for
the AfricanAmerican context study, um
this month really was continuing to look
at the Sandborn maps um going back to
all the way to about um I think 1894
um of just trying to identify
structures that are specifically called
out as belonging to the African-American
community. it seems like uh language
kind of changes after 1894 in those
descriptions. Um and so then I need to
shift to looking at city directories and
census data and things of that nature to
kind of help tell that story a bit more.
Um so that's kind of been that focus. I
did also get access to newspapers.com,
wiotra, and ancestry.com
to do a couple of more um in-depth
research when I start pulling names and
things like that, too.
Um, I also met with Megan, um, from
obviously we know from the Alliance for
Historic Wyoming, um, and she invited me
to write a, um, article for them of for
Black History Month using this research
that I'm developing from this project.
So, I think that'll be pretty great.
So, that's kind of where we're at with
that project. um hoping to get into the
city directories, like I said, in the
census data. Um Josh Chrysler obviously
on our board, he sent me some
information, too, that I need to start
digging through and taking those names
to the archives and seeing what we can
find out. So,
don't know if there's any questions
about that project.
>> Any questions on the African-American
project?
I think it's great that you'll uh have a
chance to put some of these thoughts
into an article. It'll I think that'll
help you with the nomination.
>> Oh, absolutely. At first, I was kind of
scared and then I was like, no, this
this [laughter] will be really good to
start pulling it all together into one
narrative. So, I think it'll be great
timing.
>> Terrific. All right, hearing no
questions. Let's hear about the airport
terminal.
Okay. So, airport terminal. I um
received a USB drive from Casey Worster
from Shipo. Um she has pulled together a
bunch of um architectural resources and
research and descriptions on the
building itself. So, she gave me that
USB drive for me to go through and start
to organize, which I've started to do.
Um, I think it's going to be a really
great resource for me to start writing
the architectural description and get
started on that process for the
nomination. And then Casey has offered
many times to help me fill out um the
gaps that I may have um in that. Sorry,
excuse me.
Um, and then also, um, [clears throat]
Cheryl Bean, uh, who's been working, I
know, with Amber and those guys, she
sent, um, some original blueprints of
the airport that she found in the state
archives, which are beautiful. They're
really amazing. Um, so I kind of added
those to the finals, too. And like I
said, I think this next month um to
really start pulling together that
architectural narrative um and continue
getting that pulled together. So, I'm
I'm feeling pretty good on this one,
too. We've got a lot of resources that
have come up, a lot of supportive people
for both of these projects, too. So,
it's great to see.
>> All right, colleagues, any uh questions
on that project?
[laughter]
>> All right, terrific. Um, uh, you had
mentioned in your email that just a
question about getting, uh, your
invoices paid. Um,
>> yes, I haven't received payment for, uh,
the invoices that I've sent so far.
>> Go ahead, Charles.
>> Members of the board, I did talk to you
about that, Elizabeth. Um there was a
little snafu with the way the grant was
entered through the finance department
and during the end of the year um
they've had well there's been problems
with people being able to align due to
the burning of vacation that is needed.
So it's unfortunate but we're getting it
together. Um there there was a it's my
understanding that there is a required
match of $15,000
for the for one of the grants from the
for that airport terminal. And I believe
that we are we need to have that match
paid to the city to initiate the
payment. And then there's a there was a
$3,000 match for the cultural history
one and we need to identify where that
match was coming from. I believe it was
an inind match. So I think that was
actually Kathy Taber Douglas's time with
the research. So we need to clarify
exactly where that's coming from.
>> Is there anything the board needs to do
or approve to get that match
required so we could get her paid?
>> Not yet. We and we also did lose our
grants coordinator. She resigned and
left. So we have a brand new one that
just started on
was it last Tuesday? Yeah, last Tuesday.
So we we have a couple of snafoos. We
will get that to you and Elizabeth, I'll
touch base with you on how we can get
that resolved. Apologies for the delay.
>> Okay. Thank you.
Yeah, David,
>> I just want to mention for Chuck's
benefit that we were talking about
airport terminal number two, which is
the one with the big swooping roof and
uh because the other the original
airport terminal is between that
building and that little post office on
the corner there on 8th Avenue. So,
>> yeah, it's a neat project, a midmod
structure with a lot of history.
All right, great. Um, is there any
update on oral histories?
>> Um, I don't have any updates uh this
month over the holidays. Um, except that
I'm going to get back in the swing of
things here in the next couple weeks. I
have um two more um interviews for the
the Green Door or oral history project
that um I plan to complete. One is um
with one of the um partner owners that
Charles gave me um his his name and
phone number. Haven't contacted him yet.
Um, but I want to talk to him and then
to uh one other um longtime uh patron
and employee. Um, and I think that's uh
those are my next two two steps with
that.
>> Great.
Has uh have you been using the equipment
at the library yet or?
>> I've I've just been using my personal
equipment. I found it easier to to do.
>> Okay.
Okay. Um, let's move on to Historic
Preservation Month. I would suggest that
that would be good fodder for your u
upcoming strategic planning.
Yeah, sure. Uh, how about education of
the public and historic preservation?
>> Nothing this month and I don't think
there's anything on the marketing
committee.
>> Okay. Also, good things to kind of
reassess when you um get your new plan
going.
Um, I kept showing off this really
awesome ornament and telling people
about the 399 in the corner, um, which
people thought were were very, very
neat. Um, so let's hear if there's an
update on ornaments.
>> Um, there's a lot more hidden in that
ornament than the 399, by the way.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Um, ornaments are sold out. Um, my
second printing of the capital ornament
sold out. I've collected all the money
except so if something happens to me,
the um state museum still owes us money.
I made a commitment to the governor's
wife that I'm going to do her ornament
next year separate from the one I do for
the city. So, if you guys don't have a
pro or I mean, if you have a problem
with that, I'm going to do it anyway
without your um input.
Um,
and I'll whatever I charge her, I don't
know what I'm going to charge her, but
it depends on how long it takes me to
put it together and what. And then I'll
just donate that money back to you guys.
I've got an idea for next year's
ornament. Um, I still probably, and this
is not an exaggeration, at least three
times a week get somebody calling me and
want ornaments from the past. Um, of
course I don't have them. And then on a
lighter note, uh there's a lady that
lives north of town
and she buys about 15 from me and she
meets me at the tractor warehouse in the
parking lot. And I hand her a bag of
ornaments and she hands me back a bag of
cash.
And I told her, "This is kind of looking
like a drug deal here." And oh yeah, and
she makes cookies for me. She gets she's
got the secret recipe from the Brown
Palace. and every year hands me this. I
can't wait to get it. All these cookies
and so I'm in.
>> Are you sure you want to continue, Gary?
Cuz this is a p this is a public.
>> Well, it goes south from here.
>> Okay.
>> Um and you know, it it's really been fun
and I pick up the paper and she died.
>> Oh.
>> So, um yeah, it's one of those things I
was always looking forward to and um had
a bad turn. But her story is is she
asked for the recipe at the Grand Palace
for these cookies and they said sure and
she gets her bill to check out and it
they charge her $187 for that recipe.
So she got to them and put it on the
internet and um anyway that's the way it
works. So never a dull moment in the
ornament business and uh I'll continue
to work on it for you. Gary, did we ever
um did that lady from the Casper
Historic Group call you about ornaments
ever?
>> Um the only thing they did, and I mean I
hate to say this, they wanted somebody
to do it for them. I don't think anybody
wanted to do any work. And um and that's
where we left it. I said, "I'll advise
you. I'll give you all you need, but I'm
not going to do it for you." And I never
heard back. So
um that's where we're at with that.
Well, since this is my last meeting as
chair, could you please expand on the
hidden items in the Christmas ornament?
>> I don't know if I can remember them all.
There's a letter in there. There's a guy
standing on top of Devil's Tower. Um,
Santa Claus is in there waving at you
from some point. You need to spend some
time with that.
>> I need to sit just sit down and stare at
the ornament for Okay. And those of you
for that don't know um when I started
this the second ornament um shows the
depot with a snowstorm and I made one of
the snowflakes into the co virus.
>> Right. Right. I remember that.
>> Um then when we went to the um the
fountain
um there's a hypodermic needle hidden in
there to signify the um vaccines and
there's other stuff in there. Then when
I did the governor's mansion, the tree
is draped in co masks and there's just a
lot there's a lot to it. Does the first
lady know what she's getting into with
these hidden items? here.
>> She loves
>> um Chuck, this has been um um there are
a lot of historic preservation boards
and we call them CLGs around the state,
but very few that have uh have been able
to generate their own revenue to spend
on historic preservation projects. And
Gary's been a one-man revenue generate
chain for several years now with the
sale of these ornaments. He's probably
just a warning. He's going to twist your
arm to help sell them.
>> And um just so you know, about $85,000
I've generated.
>> Yeah, it's been a serious number.
>> Oh, and by the way, we still owe the
University of Wyoming $1,752
if you get a bill for that. I had to pay
him that and that was a percentage for
putting the little bucking horse on the
ornament.
>> So, I'm still going to come to you with
a bill for that.
Yes. Questions for Gary.
>> Is it the macaroon recipe or the
chocolate chip one? Okay.
>> Just Google.
>> She told me to bring them down here and
share them with you guys, but they would
have got stale.
>> I have one more question.
>> Yes.
>> This is for uh board member Sims.
The price point has historically been
$25. I think there was discussion that
was it supposed to go up to 30 or is it
saying a 25?
>> The discussion we had was we gave a a
press release and said they'd be $25 and
the um depot museums charging 35.
>> Got it. So, um actually 25 is kind of a
stretch. I was charging that when I was
putting pieces on them and gluing in
tiles and um actually we could have make
we're doubling our money easy but um
people don't seem to bulk at 25 but I'm
afraid if you went to 30 they wouldn't
sell out as fast.
All right, thank you very much. Let's
move on to airport fountain planning. Um
so um we've
uh had this uh long-running project with
the airport fountain. It's this
beautiful terracotta historic fountain.
And we uh suffered a little bit of a
blow um trying to get towards
um allocating money that was uh willed
to the historic preservation board from
the Gwen Rice estate to use to um uh to
work on the fountain interpretation and
maintenance and signage and
beautifification and all those things.
Uh and uh we had an a situation where
the the uh restoration work that we had
uh paid to get done on that terracotta
fountain to much public celebration
um was starting to fall apart and we at
first thought that it was due to a hail
detrimental hail storm that happened
here this last season. Um, turns out it
was more complicated than that, but
we're back in a situation where we're uh
looking at needing to restore the
terracotta on that fountain. So, that's
the bad news. I guess the promising news
um is that one of the members of the
committee assigned to this, Patrick Van,
your your colleague, hopefully you'll
meet him soon, has gotten a hold of a
contractor who may be able to do this
work for a much more reasonable amount
than the masonry company that had done
the original work told us that they
would charge. And so that outfit is
called um
I have it here in my notes. uh Pacific
Coast Conservation, a woman named
Lucinda, who's been in char uh touch
with Patrick. And so I think where that
is now left um since Patrick had to step
back from that is to um get a hold of
them and get an actual bid for them to
do the restoration work on it, which I
heard was going to be something around
$7,000.
And we do have the ability to pay for
that.
>> Seven.
>> That's what I That's what I thought. I
could be out to lunch, guys. or a bit
less than that.
>> Initial second bid was 65,000.
>> Was that from the original folks?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. These people are going to come in
at much much less than that.
>> Yeah.
Um [snorts]
so that's that's good news and they are
interested in doing it. Um
so that's I think that's the followup is
to get a hold of them um with Patrick
not really being able to do a lot of
work right now and and ask them just
give us a bid on it.
Uh, and I can forward that information
to all of you in case you don't have it.
Um, because I've got the number and the
website for Pacific Coast Conservation
who he has met with in person. They
actually came here under their own
expense to look at it. So, that might be
a promising way to go there. Um,
anything on the questions on the airport
fountain? That's been such a complicated
ongoing circumstance.
Um and then we do have, you know, what I
think is a really viable um bid from an
interp a historic interpretation house
in Commerce City, um who had come up
here. Um very reasonable price,
particularly in comparison with the
other bid that we got. So, I'm hoping at
whatever point that that is we feel like
we've got a handle on all the moving
parts here that maybe there could be a
proposal to go with that bid, get the
restoration done and finally start
allocating money out of that Gwen Rice
estate towards the fountain. Gary,
>> I don't think we should leave here
tonight without assigning that to
somebody and getting it done. Longer we
put things off, more likely are we're
not to get it done. Well, that committee
still exists. It's me and Kelly at this
point. Uh, and Amber, so we can continue
to work on that
if we can get something done before next
meeting.
>> And I think that's something that we
could all look at at the strategic
planning meeting as well. And I I might
be jumping ahead here, but I I think
that instead of waiting till March, and
I know that I think that's what we did
last year was wait till March for the
strategic planning. I think we should
plan on that in the next few weeks and
maybe into February, but a little bit
sooner in the year because I think when
we wait for that strategic planning
meeting, it really hurts us for historic
preservation month because we can't we
can't get anything put together quick
enough. So, when we get to new business,
I think we should discuss when we
schedule that.
>> That sounds good. Um, so let's put that
uh we'll come back to that under new
business.
All right. Pump house. Well, uh, guess
what folks? Uh, good news. Um, after a
kind of a strange circuitous journey on
the 22nd, the, um, city council voted to
repeal the, uh, previous, uh,
resolution.
And that means repealing every aspect of
it, including the part that called for
the demolition of the building if it
hadn't been sold by a certain time
frame.
was that date going to be tomorrow? So,
um I guess to kind of simplify it the
way I look at it and and Charles, let me
know if this is an appropriate way to
think about it, it seems like the city
kind of decided to just kind of press
the reset button on this whole thing.
Just go kind of go back to square one
and um start providing an opportunity
for the community to come together and
find like collective solutions for this
whole thing. Um, so that was kind of my
take on it. Uh, it was kind of a uh nice
little pre Christmas present and it it's
kind of given the pump house a reprieve
and uh and provides for some new
opportunities and the and the council
person that if I remember correctly made
the proposal was Tom Crave
who was the person who brought the
resolution that included the demolition
provision in the first place. I could be
getting things wrong, so correct me if
I'm wrong, but is that kind of a good
way, you think, to think about it as
we're kind of just we have a a chance to
start a fresh and try to come up with
some solutions together. I think what
that means is we should now do that and
proactively
because uh it would be really
unfortunate if in a few years it came
back and somebody on the council said we
pressed this reset button in December of
2025 and nothing happened and no one
sees the opportunity or the or the new
moment. So, especially with all the
momentum around the pump house tours and
the public interaction and everything, I
think it's time to be proactive about
this one. So, I'd encourage you to also
consider that as you get into your
strategic planning,
but that's where we are on the pump
house.
>> Have a question.
>> Yeah, probably directed to you. Do we
know what's in the 55gallon drums that
are stored there that are
>> Pete that? And he told me
I asked him when we were out there on
site.
>> Chair, members of the board, that's the
second time I've been asked that
question this week. A second time in two
days. So,
um, no, we don't. Uh Paul Botti the
project manager is I directed him to
talk with Terracon to do sampling. He's
going to have them come out to do
sampling. They're environmental agency.
So he was supposed to call me and let me
know if that connection I gave him did
not work and he has not called me. So I
believe it works.
>> So basically nobody knows what's in him.
Um Pete, I think Councilman Leborn knows
a lot about it and I apologize Gary, I
can't remember what he said because I
did ask him about it. You might uh he
might be someone to talk to.
>> It's good or something.
>> And just to brief all of you, there's
probably
50 55gallon drums sitting there full of
something. and my first initial reaction
was how are you going to sell that
property to anybody when you've got that
potentially
hazardous situation sitting there. So I
think probably one of the things we
should do is find like sounds like we're
going to find out and get rid of them.
>> Yeah. Thanks. All right. Any other
questions, comments on that item?
Okay. Well, good news to start the the
new year.
watch list items. Um, we just had a
question about the house across from the
governor's mansion.
Uh, tours of schools closing Vanassel.
Any updates there? Certainly things at
Liberty obviously to consider a fresh as
you go into your planning.
Um, okay. So, that sounds like we can go
ahead and switch gears to that under new
business. Amber, would you like to
share your thoughts on the strate
strategic planning?
Yeah, I I believe that we've done it on
a Saturday in the past from I think it 9
to noon is what we've done. Um so I
think we should go ahead and schedule
that this evening if there's something I
don't know if someone wants to propose a
date in the next few weeks. I don't know
if we want to try and get it done before
our February
meeting or or maybe right after
>> for discussion. Amber, I have a variable
to throw in there and that is do you
feel like the planning session would
benefit from uh members of this board
having just come back from this?
>> That's a really good point. Maybe
>> because that's not until what the 11th
and 12th of February.
>> That's correct.
>> So maybe maybe you could plan something
between when this is over and when that
February board meeting is.
>> Yeah. No, I think that's a really good
point. Yeah. I think our next
board meeting is the 10th and then the
saving places conference is the 11th
through the 13th. So maybe February 21st
is a Saturday
if that would work. I I'd be willing to
host at my office.
>> I'll be out of town that weekend.
What about February 28th?
I should be available.
Um, Elizabeth, do you know if you have a
conflict either of those days or
anybody? So, you got you just put two
dates out, right? The 21st or the 28th.
Anybody that has a known conflict other
than Kelly for either of those dates?
You do, Gary?
>> Okay.
>> So, the 28th is maybe a little bit later
than you wanted, but it's still before
March. Barely. [sighs and gasps]
>> Do you want to go with the 28th?
>> Anyone else?
I'm good with either date.
>> I can vouch for Amber's offices as being
a really great place for a retreat. Very
nice office space there.
>> Okay. So, let's uh let please let the
minutes reflect that the meeting will be
held on the 28th.
We have a time
>> 9 to noon I think is what we've done in
the past.
So, I would also throw out just for
fodder, we've talked about this already
a little bit, but um if the if there's
an opportunity for this board to have
input on the city's new comprehensive
plan, would that would the 28th be too
late for the board to weigh in on what
you've what that would look like,
Charles?
>> Chair, members of the board, I would be
lucky to have a contract executed by
then.
>> So, that's
>> so it's not even close to too late. So
that's something that you could have as
a one of the topics anyway is to talk
about your input on the comprehensive
plan. Um
what else was I going to say about that?
Yeah. And the um obviously the the pump
house, the uh some of these things that
we've been working on this past year,
keeping the pump house, I'm sorry, the
airport planning effort going.
Um anything else you want to uh talk
about or ask the board about
on that item, new business item? I was
just going to mention [clears throat] uh
for maybe Chuck uh we send board members
to this Colorado preservation meeting
every year and usually we get try to get
the new board members to go. I don't
know if you're available on that date or
not. I put my name in as kind of a
filler because I I was there two years
ago. So, but uh uh if you're available,
you can have that spot. But I'm not sure
how many positions we've got
reservations for.
>> Yeah. And I sent this in an email to
Charles, but is there maybe would it be
possible to check with them and see if
they if my reservation could get
transferred to Chuck if he wants to go?
>> What's the date on that again?
>> So that's the 11th if I'm correct. It's
February 11th, 1213. Is that right?
>> Yes.
>> And uh I've been to it. I know many of
our board members have been to it and
staff and it is a really inspiring uh
educational
uh encouraging and stimulating thing to
do. I think it'd be a great way to jump
start your uh involvement on this board
if you've got the time and the board
does cover the your expenses for it, the
registration expenses.
>> Yeah. And there's usually transportation
down there too or you can go down on
your own if you want to.
This looks like I don't know this may be
this is for you. I don't know if that's
got information about it or not, but you
can go to their website and uh look at
the agenda and everything. And typically
folks will come back with really great
ideas. It really helps the board plan uh
what it wants to work on.
>> Chair, for clarification, are we paying
all their expenses?
>> Yeah, I'm not sure if it is it just
registration or is it also motel down
there?
Historically, it's been all expenses,
>> chair, yes is all expenses.
>> Okay. So, it's all all expenses paid uh
experience for you.
>> Usually, the the meal and and drinks,
it's just a stipen. So, they'll give you
a a fixed amount and you can choose to
>> use it as you will
app.
So, no pressure, but please uh give us
some consideration.
>> Definitely a 10. Okay, great.
>> And yeah, if they if they can just take
my name out of the prepaid one because I
think I came in maybe under the early
bird deadline, I don't know. And give
that to Chuck, that'd be great.
>> So, and then would I still be on there
then? If if he's going under with no
words.
>> Okay.
>> Yes. I believe we had four registered.
Yes. Yeah.
>> And we had specifically I thought we had
specifically had
>> we had one open for the new board member
as well.
>> Do we have a show of hands of who had
who was going to go?
>> We have five. [snorts] One, two, three.
Okay. Five. Perfect. We have
>> checks covered.
>> One, two, three. Okay. Perfect.
>> Silly because you're not going.
>> That hasn't right.
>> Yeah. Gary, I'm under new business. And
this has nothing to do with historic
preservation of Cheyenne, but it has a
lot to do with historic preservation.
Thursday night at the archaeology
meeting at the college, I'm giving a
presentation on the iceman, who is the
5,000year-old mummy that was discovered
in Europe. Um,
>> Bzano,
>> Bzano, Balszano, Italy.
>> Banano Italy.
>> And I'm doing the presentation. I went
there last year and spent a week there.
And um I've probably read and
reread everything to know about him and
that changes. But um if you want to come
out, it's free. I won't go over an hour,
believe it or not. And um I promise you,
you'll leave there knowing more than you
did when you left.
>> Thursday night, it's Thursday night,
>> 7 o'clock, the medical building at the
college, LC.
>> It's a really exciting piece of history.
I was there two years ago and uh it was
the site was closed and I couldn't go
see the Iceman, but I'm glad you did.
I'm glad you're giving a talk.
Um, okay. Any other new business?
>> Um, I actually had a question.
Elizabeth,
>> I saw in last month's minutes um I
wasn't able to ask this earlier when we
were talking about the conference that
my name was down to go to the
conference. Am I one of the five whose
hands was raised when we just did that?
>> All had raised their hands. I did. And
Amber and Patrick and David. So, one,
two, three, four, five. I guess if uh if
my reservation can be used by Chuck,
then you could probably be the fifth.
>> Chair, do you I currently have Patrick
registered, Patrick Butos, Kelly,
um Morgan from our office, Milward, and
Amber registered. So, we would take
yours and give it to somebody else.
>> I'm I'm fine sitting out if Chuck wants
to go. We could always add someone.
It's just a different registration
amount, but that's all. We could still
add anyone who wants.
>> You know what I would say, folks? We've
got the money. We're very fortunate that
we have the money to send people to
something that'll really enhance their
capabilities to be a good board member.
So, I would propose that we as many
people on this board that want to go, we
just cough up the money and so they can
go.
>> It's in Denver.
>> Great. Um, yeah, you can put me on the
list then. If we aren't restricted, I'd
love to go.
>> Thank you.
>> Do I have consensus on that?
>> Okay. So, Kelly, yeah, you're in.
>> Awesome. And I have a follow-up question
on that then for the hotel. Um, I know
the city handled registrations for the
conference. Do we need to um make hotel
reservations or are you going to handle
that for everybody as well?
>> Yeah, I don't know if they had a block
or something. Chair, members of the
board, we'll we'll make that hotel
reservation, so we're not chasing down
receipts. That always is a pain in the
neck.
So, we'll we'll take care of that. Um
there's a travel lodge with like three
L's in it, so it'll be great. I'm just
kidding. We'll get you at the conference
hotel.
>> Okay. Very good. Well, I know you're all
you're all going to uh benefit greatly
from it. Um, I had a piece of I guess
moving to old business. I was going to
ask um
Charles if or anybody if we know that
there is any update on what the
hospitals intending to do with their
possible expansion and the impact on the
Rainsford district kind of where that
is.
>> Members of the board, I'm not sure where
I left off after chatting with their COO
uh recently. We went and did a little
tour of some of the properties and
everything. Their primary focus area is
some of the structures that they own
that are pretty much to the south uh
west of the property um on 21st
22nd Street. Sorry, I'm just counting my
blocks right there. They're immediately
south of Meridian um FCU. So that's
where they're actually looking at trying
to uh do some modifications to the
structures. By modifications, I mean
their desire ultimately would be to
remove the structure, ultimate
modification,
um interim use of an area for parking,
uh future use for building expansion.
the other properties that they own which
are located on the other other side
other areas. They have indicated that
they would like to return those to
residential use and make them available
for uh purchase. Um right now we we've
talked to them a little bit. We've
mentioned that there are some obstacles
there may there is likely not historic
preservation board support. Um and there
are concerns that we have heard from
other um members of of the community
that happen to be elected. So there's a
lot of discussion that um is still to be
had. Um they are taking the information
that we've given them under advisement
and determining what their next steps
will be.
I think there was talk too about putting
the address and saying what the current
status of the building was whether it
was contributing or non-contributing
which would help because if they're
non-contributing then it would be a lot
less problem. So, and chair, members of
the of the three board member Benner, um
we did have that PowerPoint presentation
that was provided to you all that does
have that list of which ones were
contributing and also on the historic
preservation website. Uh we do have
those nominations for those two
districts, Lake View and Rainsford. Um,
both of those do they're they're online
so you can uh see what what they are.
But of the ones that they were
interested in
in demoing or exploring demolition, they
all had a level of of contribution to
the um believe it was the Rainsford
Historic District.
Yeah, that was going to be my comment is
in terms of us. I think we'd really want
to know what they're proposing to do
that would impact the the actual
contributing structures to that
district. Maybe focus on those. And
that's probably something that would be
good to talk about during the planning
session as well. How much how you want
to kind of bird dog that or influence it
or participate in that.
>> All right. Well, that was the only piece
of old business I had. Does anybody else
have anything else, Patrick? Um, just a
quick reminder to the board. Um, if
we're going to do awards
uh for the uh historic preservation
month, we need to uh start thinking
about that. And Don usually handles
that. And so I'm not sure if, you know,
I I'd be interested in picking that up.
Uh there's a couple that I'm kind of a
potential
uh a business and a a property owner
lives in the capital district that I uh
know about that I could potentially
maybe ask them to submit an application.
But um I I I don't want to run into that
situation where we're all we're
struggling at the end to try to get that
done. And we should really try to focus
that. That's a good uh event for us to
do during historic preservation month.
Just a reminder.
>> Yeah. Yeah. We put out some kind of um
announcement in the paper asking people
to submit uh proposals and the the one
house we did give it to last year was
one of the ones that was uh we received
a nomination from the public on. So be
nice to do that again. But the board
members can also nominate uh things if
they want to.
>> Yeah. Yeah, and Chuck, we do um uh two
awards per year. Uh one is for a
residential structure where the owners
have uh have been good stewards or have
done historic renovation and have
protected the history. Uh the other and
that's called the Duboce award. The
other one is L Clerk Jones award and
that one goes to a commercial property
that has done good historic preservation
work and we do the those two every year.
They get a plaque. we make a public
event out of it usually and and some
often there'll be an open house where
the public can actually tour the home or
the business. Um so that's been a real
good good thing I think for us to do and
um you will have an opportunity when you
have the strategic plan to join
committees assigned to any of these
projects you guys come up with. Um so
that'll be something interesting I think
for you. Um, okay. So, the award. So,
Patrick, if if Don is really going to
kind of step to the background, you'd be
willing to to maybe chair that effort.
Okay. And I suggest Amber that maybe his
incoming chair, a call to Don at some
point pretty soon is probably in order
just to see see what he's his plans are
and whether or not he's going to stay.
>> Okay. Um, so is there any other
business?
I'm chair members of the board. There's
one other item
>> I'll go really quick. I've actually
shortened this a lot since most of you
all are new. This is a very quick
summary. Historic preservation board 101
>> training
>> training training training. We try to
hit this every year
>> or hazing we call it.
>> I think a couple of you all haven't seen
this. I believe Miss Siver I know uh
Miss Berdick hasn't seen it and other of
you all may recognize it. Um, basically
this is the mission statement of
historic preservation board. Uh, this
comes out of your bylaws or your rules
of procedure. I forgot what document you
actually call it. We have about seven
eight different boards in our department
that we report to and everyone has a
different set of rules. um but it's to
safeguard the city's historic structures
and features, foster civic pride in the
past, promote the use of historic
districts and landmarks for the
education, pleasure, welfare of the
people of the city, and to encourage
preservation of historic integrity in
land use and development planning. Um
you all are appointed by the governing
body and I would like to note that you
all are all serving um you know in your
your terms. When you are an officer, it
is a one-year term and you are limited
to three consecutive terms. So, if ever
you are um in fear of not being able to
continue your reign, take a break and
you can come back and you're limited to
three consecutive um reigns. Um you're a
little different and you'll find this
out than other historic preservation
boards when you go to Denver. if you're
going most historic preservation boards,
their sole purpose is to be the pass
through for certified local government
grants. Um, and their other role is to
review modifications to historic
preservation or historic structures to
determine if their modifications are
appropriate. We rarely see that, but
when we do, it's a fun time. Um, your
authority is granted in Municipal Code
Chapter 2.64. Um and chapter 15.5 which
is our building code and it's all under
the umbrella of state statutes. Um 2.64
talks about your appointment. 15.5 a lot
of that goes into the parameters
regarding the design standards and
protections of the historic governor's
mansion as well as demolition of
contributing structures which I'll get
into a little bit sooner.
This is all pulled out directly from
code. We will email you this, so I'm not
planning on reading this, but these are
all of the powers and duties that you
all have. Um, number one, you're the
pass through for anything historic
preservation. Um, you're really uh
looking to if we're doing a National
Register nomination for National
Register District, which by the way,
Southeast Wyoming is home to the first
National Register District, which is at
FE Warren Air Force Base. That's the
first district. Um, and then we have
>> state of the country
>> in the state.
>> Yeah. In the state. And we have the most
historic districts of any municipality
uh in the state of Wyoming.
So, we have three slides here and I'm
just going to breeze through them
because we'll send you to this.
We'll send you a copy of this. Um,
again, uh, you all in this duty, you are
an advisory group. Um so ultimately the
governing body would be the one who has
to um ratify any um designation that you
all recommend.
>> So you heard um Elizabeth talking about
that um African-American history and the
other one some point those would go
before the city council and they would
approve them as new historic districts
in the in the city. And a lot of the
items that you really do um uh work work
towards and you you do in the community
really fall under these last two bullet
points which is really uh promoting the
public interest in preservation and also
uh just getting the word out and
recognizing the importance. A lot of
this is done with the L clerk Jones
award, the new boys award, which are
annual awards that celebrate um historic
preservation um and adaptive reuse of
buildings. Um and also just the
different projects we've done to promote
public interest in um in historic
preservation.
Um again, uh there I thought there was
only three slides. I guess there's four.
So again, here's um other other items
that we have, which is continuing to
promote historic preservation on a
community level, which you all are by
far one of the most active boards that
we have when it comes to being
selfarters and really working to promote
um the mission of historic preservation.
And I have to thank Gary for his uh
dedication for the ornaments and a lot
of the ideas he's brought to the board
when it comes to um other things he's
seen in other places like plaques and
stuff like that. And if anyone has an
old vehicle, I think Gary can help you
out with that.
So you you all do have some decision-m
authority that has been given to you
under city ordinance. Um, a lot of this
is bounded by that area in blue, which
is right south of the hospital, which is
the governor's mansion protective area.
In this area, anyone who is modifying a
historic structure um or um building a
new structure, they must come to this
board for a certificate of
appropriateness. Um unfortunately um I
remember when Josh Chrysler um myself we
had another person um he was not not
here anymore. She relocated and Lonnie
Olsen we went to the preservation
conference in Cincinnati and we were all
geared up ready to come back and start
promoting this uh district that is a
sign review district needed approval.
organ all the information out there and
then someone on 21st Street had decided
to proceed with uh a mass excavation and
partial demolition of a historic
structure. So that kind of put a wrinkle
in that and we've still been dealing
with that for quite some time. Um but we
have had a couple of um properties that
have come in front of this board for
appropriate appropriateness. One of
those most recently was on Evans um
Avenue where they did an addition on the
rear of the building. Um and then there
is a vacant lot behind the behind the
governor's mansion that had been used
for temporary construction activities uh
that um has been presented in some ways
to the preservation board for compatible
infill development. I'll get and I get a
little bit more detail on what
compatible development is in just a
moment.
Um the other item we have is uh review
of the demolition and moving of any
structures that are on our contributing
structure list. So if there is a
structure that is determined to be
contributing to a district if it is
proposed for demolition it or relocation
it must be reviewed and approved by this
board. If the board uh does
not grant any of these items a
certificate of appropriateness or
permission to demolish or move a
structure, the board of adjustment,
which is another board under the
planning and development office, would
hear the appeal. If that doesn't work
for them and there's an appeal made, um
then it would go to district court.
So, certificate of appropriateness, uh,
these are pretty standard. What you
would do is you will review any proposed
modifications to a structure um that
just alter its character and its design.
Um, our design standards are very open
and very vague and this comes from
municipal code. Really what you're
looking at is will the alteration and
modification
uh
harmonize with the period of science
history from 1890 to 1930. So that is
pretty broad because there are a lot of
different architectural styles. Um here
we just have an example of a craftsman
home which has stucco. If that were to
to happen in historic district, you
know, that would re or in the um
the governor's mansion protective
district, something like that would be
reviewed by the preservation board to
see if it harmonizes with the
architectural um period of Cheyenne's
history. In addition, there's a
provision for new construction that
shall be compatible with the mass scale
and architectural features to protect
the historic integrity of the
surrounding area. This is definitely a
unique criteria. It really is an open
door for a lot of different stuff,
especially when we have a half block
that is open for redevelopment that is
immediately south of a multi-level uh
parking garage. Um and immediately north
of the historic governor's mansion. Um
again the board of adjustment he hears
any appeal appeals on decisions
regarding certificates of
appropriateness which are oftentimes
referred to as COAs
demolition moving permit review. Um
we've taken a a look at this in a lot of
detail recently and
one of the um elements with this is this
only applies to full demolition or full
relocation of of a property.
Um we for a little bit were rereading
it, looked at it under a different lens
and we thought this could be removal or
partial demolition of a structure,
removal of historic elements, but that
is not the case with how it is worded in
title 15 of our code. So right now this
is only full demolition.
Uh so in the event that a home uh is a
contributing structure and is modified
to remove contributing features that
does not go to the preservation board at
this time.
Um there have been examples of folks
that have done renovations that may
alter the the status of a building but
those alterations have not been
documented in any um recent
architectural surveys. Uh, one that was
noted more recently that occurred was
the former Capitol City Grill um on
Capitol and 18th where that was a
building that when the nomination went
through, it was not 50 years old and not
eligible. And it was noted that if it
were to be reserveyed, it likely would
have been a a significant um
architectural style contributing to the
downtown historic district.
Now, um, even if it were classified, it
would not be reviewed by the historic
preservation board because it doesn't
fall into the criteria of being
demolished completely um, or relocated.
So, if you're looking possibly for
something you'd want to look at for a
work plan, that'd be something you could
discuss at your upcoming meeting. I do
not know what the governing body's uh
temperature would be on on that.
>> You mean on amending the provision?
>> On amending to to include partial or or
or that um
>> Okay.
>> It's just it's it's something that is
more common in other um jurisdictions.
Um, so it could be something worth
exploring.
Um, when you are uh considering any of
these demolition permits or uh
relocation permits to move a structure,
um, these are this is a summary of your
review criteria. In the event that one
of these were to move forward to you, we
would provide complete details on what
the review criteria is per code. This is
just a summary extracted from uh,
section 2.6490 of municipal code.
Um there are some special provisions
with this. If a structure has been
condemned by the building official, uh
the
uh board cannot deny that demo permit.
They're obligated to approve that. Um
which then that falls into the demo by
neglect conversation that we had in the
past. Um, and again in the governor's
mansion protective area, this applies to
all structures contributing or not in
that district. So if someone wants to
remove a shed or accessory structure or
carport or install one, it would also
apply to to those um items as well.
And in the event that it is scheduled
for a public hearing, um it is required
that a quorum show up. If the quorum
does not show up, it automatically is
approved strength provision. It's in the
municipal code.
So, expectations of roles and
responsibilities. Um, I like this
picture. It represents staff. You know,
there's a staff right there. Uh, we
don't have a dedicated staff member for
historic preservation. Um, we're we're
trying to we it has bounced around a lot
over the years. We've had many faces
that you have seen. I finally drugg
Aaron here to try to be some
consistency. She hasn't left yet. Um
Morgan is um being groomed into the
position. Um hopefully she'll be able to
take over in the future. Um but we do uh
work with our grants coordinator to um
make sure we can get the grants in
order. Um and we do uh support the
preservation board um through a variety
of efforts including um assisting with
travel um those types of items. to
facilitating these meetings and also um
taking minutes of the meetings for you
all.
Um we all know um that the board is
comprised of three officers and the
other members. Uh we still have the
secretary and is taking minutes. Sorry,
Mr. Benner. No, I'm just kidding. No, we
have the um secretary taking minutes,
but that had been the case in the past,
but we are providing that service right
now. Um the board is arranged into
subcommittees which um there are
subcommittees which you will get into
discussion at your February 28th
meeting. Um and those folks are
encouraged to meet outside the regular
meeting uh brainstorm and uh come up
with you know direction and action um on
certain projects and topics. Uh what
happens with those subcommittees is they
would put a report together. uh they
discuss that at the regular meeting and
if any action is necessary they would
take action at that regular meeting.
Subcommittees are always made up of less
than a quorum. In this case we have 11
members on the board. So a
subcommittee's maximum amount can be
five persons.
All of the agendas are posted online uh
generally a week prior to the meeting.
We really strive to be a week prior just
for best practice. Um, it doesn't always
hit that, but usually it does. It's very
easy to find.orghpb
for historic preservation board. Uh,
there's a hack to our website if you
want to get to the planning commission.
It's PC. The board of adjustment, BOA,
urban renewal authority, URA,
Downtown Development Authority. I think
you all can figure that one out. So
anyway, we we've set that up um with
little cheats to get you to the agendas
and other information on the other uh
divisions and such.
Um expparte communications, I always
talk about this. Uh this does not really
fall in line with a lot of your
decisions. This really is if or a lot of
your actions. This is really in the
event that you all have an item that you
are going to either have to approve like
a COA or an item where you're going to
make a recommendation to the governing
body to ratify and you as a voting
member that's setting a direction for an
approval um that you are getting any
specific information from another that
could influence your vote. Um you need
to try to avoid that.
Um, so that's that's what the experte
communications is. This isn't
prohibiting you from talking about the
airport fountain. This isn't prohibiting
you from talking about uh the cultural
history survey or any of your other
projects or just getting gathering
ideas. So, it's really um very limited
based on things that you will make a
decision on.
>> So, um open meetings act. This is kind
of important. Uh we've had other
communities in the state who have really
been made an example of problematic open
meetings. Um I will say that I've
updated this just a little bit to
address some of our concerns we've had
and then um kind of um remove some of
the levels of caution that I used to
exercise back in the day. Um my biggest
level of caution was trying to avoid the
perception of any type of meeting
occurring. Um, and I don't think that's
probably the best case for all of the
boards. Um, so Wyoming State statute
uh sets the standards for what an what a
meeting is and what needs to happen for
meetings. And basically a meeting is one
word business is going to be connected
or conducted keyword business will be
conducted. Um, and it has more than a
quorum. So that's or a quorum six or
more members. Um, this can include
email, text conversations, everyone
commenting on a Facebook post. It
doesn't mean you can't all go like or
say heck yeah or hell yeah to supporting
the pump house. Um, you can say that,
but if you start to have a conversation
on that feed, hey, we need to um
allocate 1300 of our dollars to this
cause. And you and Millward says, yeah,
that's great. And Josh is like, I love
it. and all a sudden Kelly's like,
"Nope."
Not that you would say that, but just
saying they start having a conversation.
That's technically an open meeting. So,
you want to try to avoid that. So, there
are some exceptions and this is new.
>> Partly, Charles, because those open
meetings have to been advertised.
>> Advertised. And the advertisement is
ethically only 8 hours prior to the
meeting under state statute. But still,
um, I put some clarification here. an
open meeting. It's not going to include
uh meetings or gatherings where there's
no discussion, no deliberation or
decision making about official business.
Um there's no presentation of
information concerning public business.
These can be items such as open houses,
award presentations, us all going on a
tour, uh us going to the grocery store,
those types of items, um hanging out at
a local brewery or something like that.
provided there is no talk on any
official business. So don't start
talking about let's make design
standards and we should do this because
that'll ultimately be something that's
decision but it could be something like
wow look at that architecture that's
beautiful.
It's a shame that they say let that that
building fall into disrepair.
So those items conflict of interest.
This is a we haven't seen this here yet
but I have seen it in a prior
preservation board. I I was secretary
to. Um
I once had a a com a historic
preservation commissioner that we called
them commissioners. They said, "Okay,
it's my turn." So they got up and walked
from one end of the table and sat on the
other one and said, "I want to present
this case so I can get a COA for
modification to my structure."
Um, so that was a one where they number
one
um should have um
recused them. Well, sorry, I'm going to
back up. That is one where they just
have a conflict of interest because they
should not be representing themsel in
that case. They should have a neutral
party that is making that presentation
because that puts inherent conflict on
all the board members because now
they're they're looking at a peer who is
um sitting in an applicant role um who
um could be unduly influencing their
decision. Likewise, a conflict of
interest would be if uh Josh lives in
the governor's mansion and historic
district and his u buddy lives right
next door and um his buddy says, "Hey,
you want to invest in um my property?
We're going to do some remodeling and I
need to go to the historic preservation
board to get a COA for the
modifications." And Josh has a financial
interest in that project. He should not
be voting on it. He should recuse
himself from any conversations and
discussions on that item.
>> And also, Charles, am I correct? Declare
the conflict.
>> Yes. And if you do have a conflict,
declare the conflict at the beginning.
We have a item on the agenda for
disclosures. It's something we have on
all of our planning and development um
agendas just to give the person the
ability to de declare a conflict or even
have the discussion if they believe a
conflict may be there. and then the
staff and the other members of the board
can say yes there appears to be a
conflict or no there doesn't. So really
uh conflict is do you have a competing
interest? Do you have monetary gain? Are
they a family member? You know those
types of items. Do do you have a
contract that you're working on and
you're voting on that contract? Like for
example, um board member Deg Grryer
chose not to vote on her own contract,
which is completely the right way to to
go.
So again, if you have any questions,
feel free to reach out to us. Uh this
that's our phone number. Our planning
and development website is easy to find.
Think of Panda. They get you there on
the shortcut.
>> I would only add that thank you Charles
for for doing this every year. Um, good
timing with our new board member. Um, my
only editorial comment would be it's a
little bit unusual to have this whole
ordinance about one block in a city.
That's that governor's mansion
protective area. And the there the the
reason for that was that part of the
integrity of the setting uh we use in
historic preservation parlance
um of that building is because at that
point in history governor's mansions
were deliberately built in residential
areas because there was a thought that
the governor should live among the
people that they represent. So
consequently, to not have residential
structures around the governor's mansion
impacts the integrity of the setting uh
and can render the governor's mansion uh
its eligibility on the national register
could put that in question. So I I
believe I'm talking for the folks who
wrote that ordinance, but that that was
a major reason that ordinance was was
created in the first place.
Unfortunately, we've despite the
ordinance seen historic structures,
residential structures be moved off of
that uh property. So, um it's something
that Charles has and has helped us keep
eyes on what they're kind of up to
there. The hospital has had it kind of
an seemingly endless construction
uh activity going on there with a lot of
temporary structures. But uh anyway,
that's it's an unusual to have that
separate ordinance for a board like
this. I wanted to give you the context
of it. I will quit blathering on and see
if anybody else has any business before
the board.
If not, I'm going to bang the gavl for
the last time. We are adjourned and I'm
going to hand it down the line here
into the capable hands of Amber Conwell.
Welcome again.
>> Thank you.